Hello English learners.
Welcome back to another
lesson here at English
pod. My name is Marko.
And my name is Catherine. Hello everyone.
Today Marko, what are we talking about?
Well, today we are
not really in the best
mood, we mean we're
kind of sad, we're kind of
nervous, we're not feeling very well.
Yeah, it's a cloudy day, maybe that's why.
The blues, the blues. So
yeah, that's what we're
talking about today.
We're going to have a lot of
different descriptive
words to express maybe
feeling sad or maybe you're
angry or you're nervous
or something like
that. Okay, well, this is a
very useful lesson.
Hopefully you're not feeling
this by, but if you have
to talk about someone who
is, you've got lots of
words for you. But first,
we're going to preview a couple in today's
vocabulary preview. Very capillary preview.
All right, so today I'm
vocabulary preview, we're
going to look at two
words. And the first one
is a way of saying that
you feel sad. So basically,
I'm feeling down. Okay,
down, you might have
heard this before because
it's the opposite of the word up.
Exactly. So you're not feeling up,
happy looking up. You're feeling down.
This is another word
for sad like Marko said.
Or you can also say I'm
a bit down today, right?
Yeah, I'm a bit down today
or you look really down.
Are you okay? Yeah,
so you look sad.
Are you, is everything okay?
So down. So now another feeling
or a way that a person
is feeling, maybe that
person is grouchy. Would
you please stop talking
so loud, Marko? I think
you have, I seriously
don't be grouchy. So
grouchy is a way someone
acts usually when they're
in a bad mood. Right.
So it's not like really
angry. You're not angry,
but you're not very happy
either. And you're not
very nice to people.
So there's a very famous
TV character called Oscar
the grouch on Sesame Street.
Look for him on YouTube
or Yoku. And he's very,
very good for learning
about this feeling grouchy
because he's a grouchy
guy. Yeah, he's always
angry or not, never
happy basically. Right.
He's always complaining
about something.
So that word again is grouchy.
All right. So after taking a
look at these two words,
we're ready now to listen
to our dialogue
for the first time.
Let's see what this dialogue
is about if maybe they're
grouchy or maybe
just sad. Fine. Okay.
I'll talk to you later.
Bye. Carrie, are you okay?
You seem a bit down.
I just got off the phone
with my boyfriend. He's
always getting upset and
losing his temper over
nothing. It's so hard to
talk to him at times.
Maybe it's just that he's
stressed out from
working or something.
He does have a pretty
nerve-wracking job, you know?
Yeah, but he's always
a really foul mood.
I tried to find out what's
bothering him or get
him to talk about his day,
but he always shuts down
and brushes me off. Men
are like that, you know.
They can feel nervous,
anxious, or on edge.
And the only way they
can express it is by trying to
hide it through aggressiveness.
I guess you're right.
What do you think I
should do? It wasn't always
his grouchy, no? Talk
to him. Try to cheer him
up when he's down
and if that doesn't work,
I say get rid of him and get a new one.
He wants something else, you know that.
All right, so two girls
talking about guys.
I guess guys have a bad
temper sometimes, right?
I think anyone can have
a bad temper, but we're
talking today about
one of the boy friend of
one of these girls who
has a very bad temper and
has been very grouchy
recently. And that's why
she's feeling a bit
down. So let's take a
look at those words now
in language takeaway.
Language takeaway. All
right, so in today's language
takeaway, we've got some
wonderful words for you.
Words that are very
good for describing stress
or having anxiety. And
the first of these words
is something you hear
all the time, especially
with young people. Right?
Somebody is stressed out.
My gosh, Marco.
I'm so stressed out.
I have 10 homework assignments
to do and softball practice.
And my mom wants me
to help quick dinner tonight.
Oh, you really are stressed out.
I am so I don't have any homework.
And I don't live with my mom.
But being stressed
out is usually
something you feel when
you have too much stuff to do.
So maybe you can be
stressed out because
of school, like in your
case, or maybe at work,
you have a lot of
things to do or a project
to finish. Right? Exactly.
And I just want to
point out here that you
can say I'm stressed or
I'm feeling stressed, but
commonly in spoken English.
So when you're
talking to your friends,
you hear this much more
often stressed out stressed out.
He's really stressed out lately.
All right. So we're stressed
out or another word
that kind of means the
same is this is nerve racking.
Nerve racking. So
nerves are those things
in our body that help
us feel things. Right?
And so something that
racks our nerves makes us
very, very tense, very
anxious, very uncomfortable.
Okay. So it makes
you very nervous. Right.
So there are some movies
that are nerve racking.
For example, suspense
movies like Hitchcock's movies
like Psycho or The Birds
or like Horror, like maybe
Saw, nerve racking. Also,
some people think that
roller coasters are nerve
racking. They're very,
very anxious when
they ride roller coasters.
Right. So let's listen to a
couple of more examples
of in different situations where we can
use this phrase nerve racking. Example one.
I think being a doctor is one of the
most nerve racking jobs in the world.
Example two. Skydiving
was one of the most nerve
racking experiences of
my life. I almost had a
heart attack. Example three.
The final match between
Brazil and Italy was
incredibly nerve racking.
And there's another way
to describe this feeling again.
It's a little bit different
but very, very similar.
We can see someone
is feeling on edge.
On edge. So this person
was feeling on edge.
But what does that mean
exactly? You're like at the end.
Why do you have to
ask so many questions?
Okay. Listen, this is
basic. Okay, Marco.
Are you mocking me
on edge today? All right.
So someone who is on
edge is easily angered. Right.
So it's very easy to make
this person upset or angry.
Someone who just quit
smoking might be on edge.
That means it's very,
very easy to get them
to be upset. Wow. So
yeah, you are on edge.
Right. Exactly. He's on
edge or he seems on edge.
Doesn't he? Okay.
Very good. Wow.
These three words that
we've just looked at are really
interesting and
very, very useful.
I guess you can describe many
different situations or a person
that's going through
these feelings, right?
Absolutely. I think there
are a thousand ways
to describe being nervous
or anxious or upset.
So maybe we should take
another listen to today's
dialogue and figure
out how exactly we use
these words and we come
back. We talk about some
other phrases that are useful.
Okay. I'll talk to you later. Bye.
Carrie, are you okay? You seem a bit down.
I just got off the phone with my boyfriend.
He's always getting upset and
losing his temper of nothing.
It's so hard to talk
to him at times.
Maybe it's just that
he's stressed out from
working or something.
He does have a pretty nerve
wrecking job, you know.
Yeah, but he's always in
a really foul mood. I
tried to find out what's
bothering him or get
him to talk about his day,
but he always shuts
down and brushes me off.
Men are like that, you
know. They can feel
nervous, anxious or on
edge. And the only way they
can express it is by trying to
hide it through aggressiveness.
I guess you're right.
What do you think I should do? He
wasn't always as grouchy, you know.
Talk to him, try to
cheer him up when he's
down and if that doesn't
work, I say get rid of him
and get a new one. He was
something else, you know
that. All right, great. So
now that we're back, we
can start with a couple
of different phrases now
on Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder. All right, so
Marco, here's the big
question. What makes you lose
your temper? Hmm. I think
what makes me lose my
temper very, very easily
is like a dirty house.
Like a dirty room. Really,
you're in a neat freak.
Not really neat freak,
but like if it's not
at least semi clean,
you know, it really, it
really bothers me. Okay,
so this great phrase,
lose your temper or
lose one's temper is is a
phrase we use in English
to describe getting angry.
All right, so maybe
you're okay, you're a little
frustrated with something,
but someone does
something like throws all
of their clothes on the floor.
Marco here says, oh, that's it.
I'm tired of this. You're
always throwing your
clothes on the floor and
that's that's an example
of Marco losing his
temper. What about you
what makes you lose
your temper? You hear this?
What is that? Oh,
drilling construction.
When people when people
tap tap tap tap tap tap tap
tap or when they like
stomp their feet feet feet.
When they nervous, when
they make noise, yeah,
and so slowly it's
like, okay, fine, calm
down, it's okay. Okay,
no seriously, stop it,
see and then all of a sudden, I just can't
stand it anymore. To explode. Exactly, so.
All right, so that's what
makes you lose your
temper, I'll be sure to
keep my eye out of for that
and not tap my pen.
All right, all right, so
okay, you lose your
temper and now there are
situations sometimes where
you need to brush someone off.
All right, or when you get brushed off
and that's not very good feeling, but this
phrase to brush someone
off, you've heard the word
brush before, it's the
word that we used to,
you know, brush your hair
or brush your teeth exactly.
When you brush someone off, it's
like saying that you're ignoring them.
Yeah, so you ignore them or
you basically tell them to go
away very subtly
sometimes or very directly.
Exactly, and so to brush
someone off is to avoid
their company, and so a
lot of times when people
are angry, they like to be
alone, so they brush you off.
So I could say, hey,
did you want to go
see that movie tonight?
No, I can't, I have to do
something tonight. And
then Marco walks away while
we're talking, he's brushing
me off, he's ignoring
me. Yeah, so it happens,
and also maybe some
people can make up excuses
and that's also brushing
someone off,
right? Right, exactly.
So to brush someone off or he
brushed me off, doesn't feel good.
All right, and well,
all of these, all of
these bad feelings, brushing
somebody off, maybe
you feel stressed out.
In the end, you always
need a good friend to cheer you up, right?
And that's what this dialogue is all about.
Exactly, and so friends
are actually the people
that do that the
best or family, I think,
and well, we can break
this phrase down because
most of it's pretty
clear, but cheer might be
a new word for some of our
lessons. Maybe we've heard
of the term cheer leader,
you know, like, give me
an egg. So cheer, or people
cheering or cheaters when the beer.
So cheer is like happiness.
So someone who can cheer you up
is someone who makes you happy.
Remember that down we had earlier, I'm
feeling down. We're trying to cheer someone
up. We're trying to make
them go up and be happy.
Exactly. So you want
to cheer up your friends,
or maybe if you're feeling a bit down, a
family member will try and cheer you up.
Do you need someone to cheer
you up, Marco? Yeah, so you know,
well, let's go have a
drink and eat some
popcorn and be cheered.
That's what cheaters
me up, or chocolate
always cheaters me up.
Oh, I know where there's
some of that. All right, so we've
taken a look at a lot
of great phrases, but the
last sentence of the
dialogue is maybe a little bit
to strange, right? When she
says, you are something else.
You know that? Something what?
Like, is she an alien? Is
your monkey? What does she
mean when she says,
you are something else?
That's a great question.
Well, this might be a little
bit hard to understand
at first, but she's saying,
I can't believe you.
There's no one like you.
You're really something
else, you know that.
So it's kind of like a
joke, but what she's saying
is, I can't believe you.
You just want to go on
and encourage me
to find another boy.
You're unbelievable. So it
could be, is it on a positive note,
or can it be both
positive and negative?
Well, here, we've got two
friends who are using it,
so it's a positive
note, but she's kind of
making fun of her
saying, I can't believe you,
but it can be negative,
like if you're fighting
with her boyfriend and
her boyfriend cheats on
her and she's like, oh, you're
really something else, you know?
You are something
else, you know that.
It's like, there's no
comparison, you're the worst.
Yeah, exactly. So
yeah, it really depends
on how this is used and
what the tone of voices,
so how someone
says it. But in this case,
I think it's kind of a joke joke, but it's
a positive meaning. Very interesting.
It's very spoken English,
as you say, because all the
words that we see there,
they're pretty simple,
but the context or the
connotation, the meaning
is very, very different
from the actual words.
Exactly. All right,
so let's listen to this
dialogue for the last time,
and then we'll come back
and talk a little bit more.
Okay, I'll talk to you later. Bye.
Carrie, are you okay? You seem a bit down.
I just got off the phone with my boyfriend.
He's always getting upset and
losing his temper, even nothing.
It's so hard to talk
to him at times.
Maybe it's just that he's stressed
out from working or something.
He does have a pretty
nerve-wracking job, you know.
Yeah, but he's always
a really foul mood.
I tried to find out
what's bothering him,
or get him to talk about his day, but he
always shuts down and brushes me off.
Men are like that, you know.
They can feel nervous, anxious, or on edge,
and the only way they can express it is by
trying to hide it through aggressiveness.
I guess you're right.
What do you think I should
do? He wasn't always
his grouchy, you know.
Talk to him, try to cheer him up when
he's down, and if that doesn't work,
I say get rid of him and get a new one.
He was something else, you know that.
So, Katherine, are you a grouchy person?
Are you happy? Do you have a bad temper?
Oh, these are, well, very
interesting questions, Marco.
Thank you for asking. You know, the first
the first time in my grouchy, no, not very
only before 9am. You're
not a morning person.
Not a morning person,
so I'm very grouchy in
the morning, but I'm
generally pretty good about
losing my temper. It
doesn't happen very often,
but I do get frustrated
with things like tapping,
or when people eat
with their mouth open.
Oh, yeah, that's terrible.
I hate that as well.
Yeah, I can't stand there. Or I really
don't like when people bite their nails.
It's kind of, it also makes
me lose my temper.
I don't know, more than
makes me lose my temper,
it's kind of annoying,
right? It is annoying.
So what makes you really
lose your temper? We say,
what makes you blow your top? Think
about an volcano. Really grinds my gears.
I would say the worst is
when somebody lies to
me, like straight in my
face, like I know they're lying.
I know you're lying
and they still just
lie straight at me. I
agree. So what's something
that really cheers you
up? Because we talked
about like going out with
a friend maybe helps you
help to cheer up, but is there
one thing, some kind of remedy?
I have actually, I like to go shopping
when I'm really excited. I mean, I won't
buy anything like clothes
or anything like that,
usually I'll get maybe
something for somebody else
or for the house or
something. It's very strange.
I hope she like clear
your mind. It's just like
walking around and
spending a little bit of money.
I don't know, it's kind
of a good remedy.
What about you? What cheers you up? I kind
of like to organize things. Really? Yeah.
So if I'm really angry or
really upset about something,
I'll alphabetize all of my books.
Wow. Yeah. So A to Z.
See, everyone has
different remedies.
So come to our
website, English part dog.
Come tell us what makes you
angry when it makes you lose your
temper or what really cheers
you up when it's you happy.
Who cheers you up? So tell us who is someone
you like to talk to when you're upset
and how do they
cheer you up? All right.
We'll see you guys there.
And also if you have questions,
comments, suggestions, you can also
leave them there in our comments section.
Please do that. So that's all for today.
Goodbye, everyone. Bye.